Guide to the Catherine Nicholson Papers, 1897-2005 and undated, bulk 1974-2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Catherine Nicholson papers 1897-2005 and undated, bulk 1974-2005
Nicholson, Catherine.
15.2 linear feet Extent: 10,528 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lesbian feminist writer and magazine publisher, resident of Durham (Durham Co.), N.C.; co-founder of SINISTER WISDOM, a multicultural lesbian literary and art journal. The Catherine Nicholson papers contain materials dating from 1897 to 2005, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1974 to 2005. Materials in the collection primarily document Nicholson's directing and theatre related activities, her work on Sinister Wisdom, and her membership in the group Old Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC). The collection comprises correspondence; personal and professional writings and supporting materials; photographic materials; publicity about theatre and of plays directed by Nicholson; audio recordings; and ephemera. Included are play scripts written by Catherine Nicholson and other playwrights, and scripts with directorial annotations by Nicholson.
RL.00950
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Also, audio recordings in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Please note that all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Catherine Nicholson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2005-2007, 2010.
Biographical Note
North Carolina native Catherine Nicholson was born in 1922 in Troy, the seat of Montgomery County. She attended Flora Macdonald College to study English and History and received a Master's degree in English from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill in 1945. Nicholson continued graduate studies at Northwestern University, earning a Master's degree in Theatre and Oral Interpretation, followed by her Ph.D. in Theatre in 1961. Nicholson spent her career in academia as a professor of drama, teaching and directing plays primarily in North Carolina and Virginia. Nicholson's interests in ancient Greece, Shakespeare, and feminism offered her rich and varied material to mine as a director and as a writer of plays, short stories, and poetry. Nicholson is best known as the co-founder of the lesbian feminist literary journal Sinister Wisdom. From 1976 to 1981, Catherine Nicholson and partner Harriet Ellenberger (also known as Harriet Desmoines) published and edited the journal, before passing control to Adrienne Rich and Michelle Cliff. Through the stewardship of several editors, Sinister Wisdom has continued into the twenty-first century, and as of 2009 is the oldest surviving lesbian literary journal. Nicholson retired to Durham, North Carolina, where she maintained involvement in lesbian activism and continued to direct plays through the 1990s.
Collection Overview
The Catherine Nicholson papers contain materials dating from 1897 to 2005, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1974 to 2005. Materials in the collection primarily document Nicholson's directing and theatre related activities, her work on Sinister Wisdom, and her membership in the group Old Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC). The collection comprises correspondence with family and friends; personal and professional writings; poetry; notes; clippings; photographic materials, including black and white and color photographs, color slides, and a cabinet card; audio cassettes; vinyl records; press kits and playbills; reviews about theatre and of plays directed by Nicholson; and ephemera. Included are play scripts written by Catherine Nicholson and other playwrights, and scripts with directorial annotations by Nicholson. The collection contains correspondence, artwork, journals, and receipts related to the publishing of Sinister Wisdom. In addition, the collection houses Nicholson's collection of audiocassettes and long-playing vinyl records, with the majority of albums related to women's music; many of these were published by Olivia Records. Printed materials have been removed and added to the Women and LGBT Rights Periodicals Collection. Use copies of audio recordings will need to be created before items can be accessed by researchers. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Addition (2010-0068) (28 items, .1 lin. ft.; dated 1984-1985 and undated) comprises letters and cards addressed to Harriet Ellenberger, primarily from Susan Thompson.
Subject Headings
Desmoines, Harriet; Feminism -- United States; Feminism and theater -- United States; Lesbian activists -- United States; Lesbian dramatists; Lesbian feminism -- United States -- Periodicals; Lesbian feminism -- United States; Lesbian theater; Lesbians -- United States; Nicholson, Catherine; Old Lesbians Organizing for Change; Olivia Records; Playwriting -- Drama; Rich, Adrienne Cecile; Sinister wisdom; Theater -- United States; Women dramatists, American; Women in the theater; Women -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Women theatrical producers and directors -- United States; Women -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women's music; Audiocassettes; Cabinet photographs; Clippings; Ephemera; Long-playing records; Playbills; Press kits; Scripts (documents); Slides; Thompson, Susan; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Related Material
Rainbow Triangle Oral History Interviews
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
James T. Sears Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Mab Segrest Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Catherine Nicholson Papers, 1897-2005 and undated, bulk 1974-2005, (17 boxes)
  Materials are arranged alphabetically, followed by audio and oversized materials. Plays are listed by title, and other writings are listed by author. Printed materials have been removed and added to the Women and LGBT Rights Periodicals Collection.
  [Original recordings are closed to research. Use copies need to be created before content can be accessed.]
  - AIDS/HIV, 1991 and undated (Box 1)
  - Albright genealogy, undated (Box 1)
  - American Theatre Association Women's Program Convention, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Angels of Power, Sandra Shotlander, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Ashes, Ashes We All Fall Down, Martha Boesing, 1982 (Box 1)
  - At the Foot of the Mountain, 11 (1), 1985 Fall (Box 1)
  - The Attic, Patricia Green, 1988 (Box 1)
  - August Odyssey, short story, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Baby books, 1914; 1922 (Box 1)
    The earlier baby book belonged to Nicholson's older sister Edna, who died during Nicholson's childhood.
  - Because the Dawn, Amy Goldstein, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Beginnings of stories, 1950s; 1975 (Box 1)
  - Between the Acts notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Broadcloth, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Buttons, undated (Box 1)
  - Buttons for Desert, Judith Katz, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Case, Sue Ellen, undated (Box 1)
  - Cherry, Wynn, Hearing Me Into Speech, undated (Box 1)
    Nicholson's comments on Cherry's article about lesbian feminist publishing in North Carolina. Article discusses Sinister Wisdom and Nicholson.
  - Cliff, Michelle, Passing: The Fear of Difference and the Denial of Wholeness, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings about friends, 1957-1995 and undated (Box 1)
  - College essays, 1951-1955 (Box 1)
  - The Constant Journey, Monique Wittig, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1959 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1961-2005 and undated (18 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Alice and Bates, 1963-1972 and undated (Box 3)
  - Curb, Rosemary, 1984-1986 and undated (Box 3)
  - Directing notebook, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Dissertation, The Chorus as a Ritual Element in Greek Tragedy, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Diversity for Durham, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Dreams, 1975-1984 and undated (Box 3)
  - Dress Suits to Hire, Holly Hughes, undated (Box 3)
  - Durham lesbian writings, 1994-1995 and undated (Box 3)
  - Ellenberger, Harriet, 1984-1985 and undated (Box 3)
  - Event booklets, 1982; 1990 (Box 3)
  - Event fliers and reviews, 1959-2002 and undated (Box 3)
  - Feminist drama articles, 1988-1989 and undated (Box 3)
  - Feminist and lesbian theatre and drama, 1981-1991 and undated (Box 3)
  - Flight of the Mind writing workshop, undated (Box 3)
  - Flora MacDonald College, Ralph Page, 1916 (Box 3)
  - Flora MacDonald College reunion, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Flora MacDonald writings and poem, 1973 and undated (Box 3)
  - Flora MacDonald College yearbook, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Florence, Alice Childress, 1949 (Box 4)
  - The Franny Chicago Play, Judith Katz, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Gantt, Harvey, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Gay and lesbian theatre, local, 1991-1995 and undated (Box 4)
  - Goddard College theatre, 1982-1984 (Box 4)
  - Goodnight, Desdemona clippings and reviews, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Goodnight, Desdemona notebook, 1991 (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Harris, Bertha, 1972 and undated (Box 4)
  - Harris, Lois, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Heyward, Carter, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Hicks Lynn, Full Circle Farm, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Hoagland, Sarah, 1993 and undated (Box 4)
  - Hopkins, Lea, Womyn I Have Known You, 1978 (Box 4)
  - How I Learned to Drive, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Important clippings, 1992-1993 and undated (Box 4)
  - International Tribune testimony script, undated (Box 5)
  - Isadora Duncan lecture, undated (Box 5)
  - Isadora Duncan notes, undated (Box 5)
  - Journal entries, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Justice, Willa poems, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
  - Kendall, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - Kitchen Table Women of Color Press, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Langa, Helen, Reading the Fine Print: Art and Social Justice in the 1930s, 2000 January 07 (Box 5)
  - Last Summer at Bluefish Cove, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Lee, Anne, 1981 and undated (Box 5)
  - The Lesbian Anti-Rape Packet, 1976 August (Box 5)
  - Lesbian Clippings, 1992 and undated (Box 5)
  - Lesbian Contradictions, 30, 1990 Spring (Box 5)
  - Lesbian Health Center, undated (Box 5)
  - Lesbian history, 1978; 1993 (Box 5)
  - Lesbian publications, organizations, etcetera, 1992 and undated (Box 5)
  - Lesbian publishing, 1976; 1990 and undated (Box 5)
  - Lesbian theatre articles, 1990 and undated (Box 5)
  - Lesbian Writer's Conference, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Lesbians in academics questionnaire, 1994 (Box 5)
  - The Libretto of the Opera of Marie Laveau, Aishah Rahman, circa 1981 (Box 5)
  - Libraries and education, undated (Box 5)
  - Local gay and lesbian activism, 1992-1994 and undated (Box 5)
  - Love Song for an Amazon, Martha Boesing, undated (Box 5)
  - Machinal, Sophie Treadwell, 1928 (Box 6)
  - The Madwoman of Chaillot, undated (Box 6)
  - Maiden Rock, 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Margins, 23, 1975 August (Box 6)
  - Mariani, Paul, The Sign, undated (Box 6)
  - Material for poetry, 1989-1992 (Box 6)
  - Matt and Millie, undated (Box 6)
  - Matt and Millie discarded scenes, undated (Box 6)
  - Matt and Millie older version, undated (Box 6)
  - Matt and Millie, 1994 (Box 6)
  - Matt and Millie play notes, 1981-1988 (Box 6)
  - McDaniel, Judith poem, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1981-1986 and undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous writings by others, undated (Box 6)
  - Morgan, Ramona funeral, 1997 October 19 (Box 6)
  - Morton, Nelle, 1977-1985 (Box 7)
  - Murray, Gilbert, Jane Ellen Harrison: An Address, 1928 (Box 7)
  - Narratives conference, 1991 (Box 7)
  - National Lesbian Conference, 1989-1991 (Box 7)
  - National Women's Studies Association, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Nicholson, Mike, 1932-1966 and undated (Box 7)
    Papers belonging to Nicholson's father or related to his death. Includes a condolence telegram from North Carolina Representative Charles Raper Jonas.
  - North Carolina Lesbian and Gay Political Action Agenda, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Northwestern University, 1956-1957 (Box 7)
  - Notebooks, 1983; 1987; 1993 and undated (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Notes on writing, 1979 and undated (Box 7)
  - Oedipus play, undated (Box 7)
  - Old Lesbians Organizing for Change, 1989-2004 (folders 1-2 of 3) (Box 7)
  - Old Lesbians Organizing for Change, 1989-2004 (folder 3 of 3) (Box 8)
  - Old Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC) (Box 8)
    - Ageism, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - Aging, 1987-1993 and undated (Box 8)
    - Facilitator's handbook, Confronting Ageism, 1992 (Box 8)
    - Healey, Shevy, 1991-1995 (Box 8)
    - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, Durham conference, 1993 (Box 8)
    - Summer gathering, 1998 (Box 8)
    - University of Georgia leisure study, 1995 (Box 8)
    - West Coast celebration, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
  - Older Women's League (OWL), local, 1993-1994 (Box 8)
  - An Oral Herstory of Lesbianism, 1979 (Box 8)
  - Our Own Place grant application and Newsletter, 1992 (Box 8)
  - Passages conference, 1993 (Box 8)
  - Photographic materials, 1897-2002 and undated (Box 9)
    Photographs document Nicholson's life from childhood through 2002, including friends and relatives, animals, art, promotional theatre images, and her trips across the globe to Greece, England, Switzerland, and France. Travel pictures typically appear on color slides.
  - Pinball, Allison Lyssa, 1983 August 07 (Box 10)
  - Playbill, 1986; 1989 (Box 10)
  - Play plots, undated (Box 10)
  - Poems, early versions, 1974 and undated (Box 10)
  - Portia Faces Life and Stands Up For Herself, for North Carolina AAUW Convention, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Progressive causes, 1991 (Box 10)
  - Psychology, 1976 and undated (Box 10)
  - Queer theory articles, undated (Box 10)
  - Rado, Maria, The Embrace, undated (Box 10)
  - Rainbow Triangle Oral History Project, undated (Box 10)
  - Randolph-Macon Woman's College theatre, 1957-1966 (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Retirement, North Carolina, 1989-1991 and undated (Box 10)
  - Rich, Adrienne, Particularity, 1982 August (Box 10)
  - Robinson, Margaret, Stroke, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Rounds and canons songbook, 1976 (Box 10)
  - Roomers of the House, Mary Moran, undated (Box 10)
  - Sanskrit, v.5, no.2, 1974 (Box 10)
  - Scenes from the Twentieth Century Stage: Black Theatre in Photographs, 1983 (Box 10)
  - The Search for Emily, Brian Marsh, 1988 (Box 10)
  - Sears, James T., Generations, 1995-2000 (Box 10)
  - Segrest, Mab, Into the Twenty-first Century: The Dangers of Right-Wing Feminism, 1990 October 06 (Box 10)
  - She is Still Burning e-journal, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
    Feminist web journal published by Harriet Ellenberger from 2000 to 2003.
  - Shewolf's Directory of Wimmin's Lands and Lesbian Communities, 1994-1995 (Box 10)
  - Sinister Wisdom, 1976-1981 (Box 11)
    - About reviews, 1976-1977 (Box 11)
    - Ads/Listings, 1976-1980 (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - Age and aging, 1978 and undated (Box 11)
    - Anthology, 1981 (Box 11)
    - Artwork and layout, 1970s (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Book of procedures, 1980-1981 (Box 11)
    - Bookstore correspondence of possible interest, 1976-1980 (Box 11)
  - Sinister Wisdom, 1976-1981 (Box 12)
    - Boundary notes, undated (Box 12)
    - Comments from subscribers, 1977-1980 (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Content ideas, 1976-1979 and undated (Box 12)
    - Correspondence/subscriptions, 1976 (Box 12)
    - Flyers and forms, samples, 1976-1979 and undated (Box 12)
    - Humanism, 1970s (Box 12)
    - Joan Corbin's copies of The Ladder, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Journal, 1976; 1979-1980 (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Sinister Wisdom, 1975-1992 (Box 13)
    - Origins, 1975-1992 (Box 13)
    - Photographs, 1970s (Box 13)
    - Post office information, 1978-1980 and undated (Box 13)
    - Receipts, 1977-1979 (Box 13)
    - Reviews, 1977-1980 (Box 13)
    - Submission forms without correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 13)
    - Surviving Female, 1973; 1979 and undated (Box 13)
    - Turnover, 1979-1981 (Box 13)
    - Women in Distribution, 1977-1981 (Box 13)
  - Sister Heathenspinster's Almanac and Lunation Calendar, 1976 (Box 13)
  - Sleeping Beauty: A Lesbian Fairy Tale, 1971 (Box 13)
  - Songbook for Seneca Falls Wimmin's Peace Encampment, circa 1983 (Box 13)
  - Stansbury, Lucy drawings, undated (Box 13)
  - Tarot, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Theatre curricular, 1980s (Box 13)
  - Thoughts on theatre, undated (Box 13)
  - Tribes: A Play of Dreams, Judith Katz, 1980 (Box 13)
  - Twenty-two Short Plays from the Little Theatre of the Green Goose, undated (Box 14)
  - Tyrel, Hailey, I'm Sorry, But I Must Decline (from an interview with C. Nicholson), undated (Box 14)
  - Unfinished Women Cry in No Man's Land While a Bird Dies in a Gilded Cage, Aishah Rahman, 1977 (Box 14)
  - University of North Carolina-Charlotte course, Surviving Female, 1976 (Box 14)
  - University of North Carolina-Charlotte theatre, 1967-1971 (Box 14)
  - War Torn photocopies, undated (Box 14)
  - Wetzel, Kathryn, Erotic Story #1, 1982 (Box 14)
  - What Difference Does Difference Make? conference, 1992 May 29-31 (Box 14)
  - Women as artists, 1974-1975; 1994 and undated (Box 14)
  - Women in cinema, 1975; 1990-1997 (Box 14)
  - Women in print, 1976-1977 and undated (Box 14)
  - Women in Theatre festival, Boston, 1986-1987 (Box 14)
  - Women's Action Agenda, 1991 (Box 14)
  - The Women's Experimental Theatre, 1980-1981 (Box 14)
  - Women's Wisdom Corporation, 1974-1978 (Box 14)
  - Audio Cassettes, 1970s-1995 and undated (Box 15)
    Primarily contains recordings about Jane Ellen Harrison (1850-1928), British scholar and early feminist who Nicholson became interested in during the 1970s. Also includes: Are We Really Out of the Closet?; recordings of co-op meetings; a recording of Nicholson's aunt Izora; Nelle Morton's 1979 address at the National Mission Conference; Nicholson with Susan Wood-Thompson; Nicholson with Harriet Ellensberger; Ralph presentation; Religion; Adrienne Rich's Soundings; Shoulder to Shoulder; and several unlabeled cassettes.
    [Original recordings are closed to use. Listening copies must be made before contents can be accessed.]
  - Vinyl Records, 1954-1982 (Box 16)
    - Adam, Margie, Songwriter. Dixon, CA: Pleiades Records, 1976 (Box 16)
    - Baez, Joan, Self-titled. New York: Vanguard Stereolab, circa 1960. (Box 16)
    - Baez, Joan, From Every Stage. Hollywood, CA: A and M Records, 1976. (Box 16)
    - Baez, Joan. Joan Baez in Concert Part 2. New York: Vanguard, 1963. (Box 16)
    - Barrett, Sweet Emma. Sweet Emma Barrett and her New Orleans Music. New Orleans: Southland Records, 1963. (Box 16)
    - Be Be K'Roche. Self-titled. Los Angeles: Olivia Records, 1976. (Box 16)
    - Bishop, Heather. Grandmother's Song. Woodmore, Manitoba: Mother of Pearl Records, 1979. (Box 16)
    - Christian, Meg. Face the Music. Los Angeles: Olivia Records, 1977. (Box 16)
    - Christian, Meg, I Know You Know. Los Angeles: Olivia Records, 1974. (Box 16)
    - The Clancy Brothers adn Tommy Makem, The Rising of the Moon. Los Angeles: Tradition Records, 1959. (Box 16)
    - Dickens, Hazel and Alice Gerrard, Won't You Come and Sing For Me? New York: Folkways Records, 1978. (Box 16)
    - Dobkin, Alix, xxAlix. New York: Women's Wax Works, 1980. (Box 16)
    - Dobkin, Alix featuring the Lesbian Power Authority. Living with Lesbians. New York: Women's Wax Works, 1975. (Box 16)
    - Elizabethan and Jacobean Music. New York: Vanguard, 1954. (Box 16)
    - Fitzgerald, Ella and Count Basie. A Classy Pair. Beverly Hills, CA: Pablo Records, 1982. (Box 16)
    - Garland, Judy. Judy at Carnegie Hall. Los Angeles: Capitol Records, 1961. (Box 16)
    - Garland, Judy. The Best of Judy Garland. New York: Decca Records, 1963. (Box 16)
  - Vinyl records, 1958-1988 and undated (Box 17)
    - Gazette with Pete Seeger. Self-titled. New York: Folkways Records, 1958. (Box 17)
    - Great American Speeches. New York: Caedmon Publishers, 1958. (Box 17)
    - Holiday, Billie, The Original Recordings. New York: Columbia Records, 1973. (Box 17)
    - Lang, K. D., Shadowland. New York: Sire Records, 1988. (Box 17)
    - Lavender Jane. Loves Women. New York: Women's Wax Works, 1973. (Box 17)
    - Lesbian Concentrate: A Lesbianthology of Songs and Poems. Los Angeles: Olivia Records, 1977. (Box 17)
    - Lillie, Beatrice. An Evening with Beatrice Lillie. London: London Records, 1955. (Box 17)
    - McRae, Carmen. Love Songs. New York: Accord Records, 1982. (Box 17)
    - Minnelli, Liza. Liza With A "Z". New York: Columbia Records, 1972. (Box 17)
    - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, Divertimenti for Wind Instruments. New York: The Musical Heritage Society, undated. (Box 17)
    - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, Divertimento No. 15 In B Flat for Two Horns and Strings. New York: Nonesuch Records, undated. (Box 17)
    - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus, Four Piano Concertos. Music Guild Records, undated. (Box 17)
    - Near, Holly. Fire in the Rain. Ukiah, CA: Redwood Records, 1981. (Box 17)
    - Near, Holly. Imagine My Surprise! Ukiah, CA: Redwood Records, 1978. (Box 17)
    - Near, Holly and Ronnie Gilbert. Lifeline. Oakland, CA: Redwood Records, 1983. (Box 17)
    - Near, Holly with Jeff Langley. You Can Know All I Am. Ukiah, CA: Redwood Records, 1976. (Box 17)
  - Vinyl records, 1954-1984 (Box 18)
    - Parker, Pat and Judy Grahn, Where Would I Be Without You. Los Angeles: Olivia Records, 1976 (Box 18)
    - Previn, Dory, Self-titled. Burbank, CA: Warner Bros. Records, 1974 (Box 18)
    - Previn, Dory, Mary C. Brown and the Hollywood Sign. Los Angeles: United Artists Records, 1972. (Box 18)
    - Russ, Joanna. Joanna Russ Interpreting Her Stories. New York: Alternate World Recordings, 1976. (Box 18)
    - Shear, Linda. A Lesbian Portrait. Northampton, MA: Old Lady Blue Jeans, 1977. (Box 18)
    - Smith, Bessie. Any Woman's Blues. New York: Columbia Records, 1970. (Box 18)
    - Sweet Honey in the Rock. Self-titled. Chicago: Flying Fish Music, 1976. (Box 18)
    - Thomas, Dylan, Dylan Thomas Reading His Complete Recorded Poetry. New York: Caedmon Records, 1963 (Box 18)
    - Thomas, Dylan, Selections From the Writings of Dylan Thomas Read By the Poet. New York: Caedmon Records, 1957 (Box 18)
    - The Threepenny Opera. New York: MGM Records, 1954. (Box 18)
    - Trull, Teresa. The Ways A Woman Can Be. Los Angeles: Olivia Records, 1977. (Box 18)
    - Tyson, Willie. Self-titled. Madison, TN: Lima Bean Records, 1979. (Box 18)
    - Tyson, Willie. Full Count. Washington, D.C.: Lima Bean Records, 1974. (Box 18)
    - Vaughan, Sarah. Sarah plus 2. New York: Roulette Records, 1962. (Box 18)
    - Vogl, Nancy. Something to Go On. Oakland, CA: Redwood Records, 1984. (Box 18)
  - Oversize Material (Box 18)
    - Photographs and artwork (Box 19)
      Materials featuring Nicholson or created by friends.
    - Posters, 1970s-1990s (Opaperfolder 1, Box 19)
- Accession (2010-0068)1984-1985 and undated, (1 box) (Box 19)
  Addition (2010-0068) (28 items, .1 lin. ft.; dated 1984-1985 and undated) comprises letters and cards addressed to Harriet Ellenberger, primarily from Susan Thompson. Arranged chronologically.
  - Letters and cards (Box 20)